Finding Aid for Richard I. Ford papers, 1968-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Professional Service and Activities
  - Independent Conferences
    - San Juan Pueblo, When Cultures Meet, "The New Pueblo Economy," 1984 (Box 23)
    - School of American Research
      - General Materials 1978-1979 (Box 23)
      - Black Mesa Archaeological Project, Advanced Seminar, "People and Plants on Prehistoric Black Mesa," 1982 (Box 23)
      - China Through Scholars' Eyes, Touring Seminar 1982, 2 folders (Box 23)
      - Explanation of Prehistoric Organizational Change, "Advanced Seminar," Evolutionary Ecology and the Evolution of Human Ecosystems," 1971 (Box 23)
      - The Hopi Indians, Advanced Seminar 1982 (Box 23)
      - The Tewa Group, Advanced Seminar, "Tewa Ethnoscience and Ecology: Tradition and Place," 1981 (Box 23)
    - University of California, Los Angeles, Conference on American Folk Medicine, "Communication Networks and Information Hierarchies Among Western North American Indians," 1973 (Box 23)
    - University of California, Santa Cruz, Columbus Quincentenary Symposium 1991 (Box 23)
    - Smithsonian Institution, "Indication of Domestication in Indigenous North American Plants," 1987 (Box 23)
    - Wake Forest University, Worlds Transformed, "Food and the Changing Ecology of Post Columbian America," 1992 (Box 23)
    - Wenner-Gren Foundation for Anthropological Research
      - Morelos, Mexico, Morelos in a Global Economy 1989 (Box 23)
      - Tarrytown, NY, Anthropological Priorities in the Next Decade and the Role of the American Anthropological Association, "Anthropology in the Academy," 1993 (Box 23)
    - Yale University, Maize Symposium 1984 (Box 23)
  - Lectures
    - Andrews University, "Traditional Environmental Knowledge and Contemporary Biological Resource Management," 1998 (Box 24)
    - Announcements and Flyers (Box 24)
    - Cincinnati Museum of Natural History, "Native American Farming and Gardening Systems: Archaeological and Ethnological Perspective on food production," 1987 (Box 24)
    - Dartmouth College
      - "Genetic Change from Prehistoric Hands: The Sociocultural Basis for Plant Domestication," 1986 (Box 24)
      - "Domestication and Human Selection," 1986 (Box 24)
    - "Humanistic Applications of Prehistoric Archaeology," undated (Box 24)
    - International Congress of Ethnobiology, "Landmarks in Ethnobiology," undated (Box 24)
    - "Martin Aguilar," undated (Box 24)
    - Miami University, "Reinterpreting Early Agriculture in the Southwest," 1984 (Box 24)
    - "Museum: At the Core of Liberal Arts Education," undated (Box 24)
    - Oberlin College, "Evolution of Human Ecosystems," 1973 (Box 24)
    - "100 Years of Ethnobotany," Janaki Ammal Medal Lecture undated (Box 24)
    - Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México, "Plant Ecology, Biodiversity, and Prehistoric Land Management Systems in Northern New Mexico, USA," 1998 (Box 24)
    - University of British Columbia, Botany 80: Meeting of North American Botanists, "Ethnobotany in North America: An Historical Phytogeographic Perspective," 1980
    - University of Michigan
      - Distinguished Senior Faculty Lecture, "Metaphors in Stone: Interpreting Rock Art in New Mexico," 2005 (Box 24)
      - Mathaei Botanical Gardens, Ethnobotanical Trail 1997 (Box 24)
      - Phi Kappa Phi 1997 (Box 24)
      - "Skeletons in the Closet: Museums and the Collection and Display of Human Beings," 2005 (Box 24)
    - University of Tennessee, Visiting Lecture Program 1983 (Box 24)
    - University of Washington, "The Anthropogenic Landscape in Prehistoric North America," 1985 (Box 24)
    - Utah State University, "Evolving Americas: Land and Life," Lecture Series 1981 (Box 24)
    - Vanderbilt University, "Archaic Agriculture and the Rise of Civilization," 1970 (Box 24)
  - Reviews
    - Editorial Reviews
      - Academic Press, Inc. 1992 (Box 24)
      - Cambridge University Press 1977-1981, 9 folders (Box 24)
      - Case Studies in Ethnobotany, 1997 (Box 24)
      - Herb Research Foundation 1983-1987, 2 folders (Box 24)
      - Journal of Archaeological Science, 1986 (Box 24)
      - Journal of Ethnobiology, 1981-1989, 2 folders (Box 24)
      - Natural History, 1969-1970 (Box 24)
      - Reviews in Anthropology, 1979-1985 (Box 24)
      - Syracuse University Press 1990 (Box 24)
      - Thomas Jefferson Press 1990 (Box 24)
      - University of Oklahoma 1997 (Box 24)
    - External Reviews
      - Bowdoin College 1989-1990 (Box 24)
      - California Academy of Science (Box 24)
      - Carnegie Museum 1983-1984 (Box 24)
      - Center for Human Growth and Development, Ann Arbor 1992 (Box 24)
      - Joseph Carleton Wilder, Editor, Journal of the Southwest 1991 (Box 24)
      - MacArthur Foundation 1994 (Box 24)
      - Museu Goeldi (Box 24)
      - National Institute for the Environment 1994 (Box 24)
      - New Mexico State University Museum (Box 24)
      - Secwepmc Cultural Education Society 2004 (Box 24)
      - Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History 1998 (Box 24)
      - State University of New York at Albany 1988 (Box 24)
      - University of California, Riverside (Box 24)
      - University of Pittsburgh 1991, 2 folders (Box 24)
      - University of Kentucky, Lexington 1976-1990 (Box 25)
      - University of North Carolina Chapel Hill 1998 (Box 25)
      - University of Texas 1990 (Box 25)
      - University of Toronto 1996 (Box 25)
      - University of Washington, Burke Museum, Seattle 1982 (Box 25)
      - University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee 1990, 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Internal Reviews
      - Department of Anthropology Internal Review 1988, 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Tenure and Promotion Reviews
      - Adler, Michael 1996 (Box 28)
        [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2039 ]
      - Bierwert, Crisca 1998 (Box 28)
      - Ford, Richard I. 2002 (Box 28)
      - Hansen, Julie 1992 (Box 28)
      - Stephens, Sharon 1998 (Box 28)
      - Strassman, Beverly 1998 (Box 28)
- Teaching
  The Teaching series, 1969-2004 (1.0 linear foot), includes the subseries academic appointments, administrative materials, correspondence, and syllabi and course materials. The academic appointments subseries includes personnel records, appointment notices, and notes from Ford's tenure as dean and chair. The administrative materials subseries documents Ford's duties outside the classroom, including service on committees and boards, dissertation committees, the ethnobotany program, and student advising. This subseries also includes copies of Ford's curriculum vitae. The correspondence subseries includes letters to and from Ford over the course of his teaching career, as well as letters of recommendation for his graduate and undergraduate students. The final subseries, syllabi and course materials, contains syllabi and teaching-related materials for the anthropology, archaeology, and botany courses taught by Ford at the University of Michigan and at Southern Methodist University's programs at Fort Burgwin in Taos, New Mexico.
  - Academic Appointments
    - General (Box 25)
    - Chairmanship (Box 25)
    - Colorado College (Box 25)
    - Deanship (Box 25)
    - Personnel Records (Box 25)
    - Thurnau Professorship (Box 25)
    - Wayne State (Box 25)
  - Administrative Materials
    - Committees and Board (Box 25)
    - Curricula Vitae (Box 25)
    - Dissertation Committees (Box 25)
    - Ethnobotany, 4 folders (Box 25)
    - Evaluations (Box 25)
    - Graduate Advising (Box 28)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2084 ]
    - Honors Program (Box 26)
    - Student Assistants (Box 26)
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - 1969-1971 (Box 26)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 26)
      - 1983 (Box 26)
      - 1998 (Box 26)
    - Student Letters of Recommendation
      - A-C (Box 28)
      - D-G (Box 28)
      - H-K (Box 28)
      - L-N (Box 26)
      - O-P (Box 28)
      - R-S (Box 26)
      - T-Z (Box 28)
  - Syllabi and Course Materials
    - University of Michigan
      - Anthropology 173, Introduction to Cultural Anthropology, Summer 1968 (Box 26)
      - Anthropology 175, World Prehistory, Fall 1968 (Box 26)
      - Anthropology 204, The Evolution of Man undated (Box 26)
      - Anthropology 285, Cult Anthropology, Winter 1997 (Box 26)
      - Anthropology 286, Food in Human Affairs undated (Box 26)
      - Anthropology/Botany 342, Ethnobotany, Fall 1986 (Box 26)
      - Anthropology 398, Honors in Anthropological Archaeology, Fall 1999, Fall 2003 (Box 26)
      - Anthropology 405, New World Prehistory, Winger 1968 (Box 26)
      - Anthropology 418, Archaeology of Africa, Fall 1972 (Box 26)
      - Anthropology 436, Museum Techniques undated (Box 26)
      - Anthropology 478, European Prehistory, Winter 1969 (Box 26)
      - Anthropology 487, Archaeology of North America undated (Box 26)
      - Anthropology 493, Environmental Archaeology, Winter 1997 (Box 26)
      - Anthropology/Botany 509, Ethnobotany undated (Box 26)
      - Anthropology 524, Prehistoric Cultural Ecology undated (Box 26)
      - Anthropology 578, European Prehistory, Winter 1968 (Box 26)
      - Anthropology 589, Ecological Approaches in Cultural Anthropology: Prehistoric Human Ecology undated (Box 26)
      - Anthropology 654, Cultural Ecology, Spring 1968 (Box 26)
      - Anthropology/Botany/Geology 826, Quaternary Seminar, Winter 1976, 2 folders (Box 26)
      - Biology 800, Ethnobotany Seminar, Spring 1991 (Box 26)
      - University Course 252, Foodways of Humanity, Fall 2004 (Box 26)
    - Southern Methodist University, Fort Burgwin
      - 1987-1990, 3 folders (Box 26)
      - 1991, 2 folders (Box 27)
- University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology
  Materials in the University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology series, 1969-2005 (0.5 linear feet), primarily consist of correspondence to and from Ford, related to his work as curator and, later, director of the museum. Also included in the series is information on the museum's work with a film project, as well as a Micaceous pottery exhibit.
  - Conservation Procedures (Box 27)
  - Correspondence
    - 2002 (Box 27)
    - 2003, 7 folders (Box 27)
    - 2004 (Box 27)
    - 2005 (Box 27)
  - Ethnology Range
    - General, 2 folders (Box 27)
    - Correspondence
      - 1969 (Box 27)
      - 1970 (Box 27)
      - 1971 (Box 27)
      - 1972 (Box 27)
      - 1973 (Box 27)
      - 1974 (Box 27)
  - Melvin Gilmore Films 1972-1974 (Box 27)
  - Micaceous Pottery Exhibit (Box 27)
  - Jeff Parsons 2005 (Box 27)
- Audio-Visual Series
  The final series, Audio-Visual Series, 1970-1997 and undated (0.3 linear feet), includes photographs and slides of Ford alone, as well as in the field with colleagues. The slides include Ford's 1982 travels in China.
  - Audio Cassettes
    - Sacred Space 1989 (Box 27)
    - Tuesday AM Smart (Box 27)
    - Untitled (Box 27)
  - Photographs 1970-1997 (Box 27)
  - Slides 1980-1983 (includes China trip) (Box 27)
- Miscellaneous and Restricted Files
  - Restricted files removed from earlier boxes (Box 28)
  - Digital Media
    - Recordable Compact Discs, 4 optical disks CDs
      - Correspondence (Box 28)
      - Manuscripts/Research (Box 28)
      - Museum of Anthropology Business (Box 28)
      - University Reports/External Committee Reports (Box 28)
    - Untitled Zip Disk, 1 zip disks